[Music]
recently the World Health Organization
classified processed meat also known as
cured meat bacon ham hot dogs lunch meat
sausage as definitively cancer causing
in humans as if that's not enough High
processed meat consumption has also been
associated with increased risk of dying
prematurely from all causes put together
and is a risk factor for several major
chronic diseases such as type two
diabetes coronary heart disease and
stroke what about lung issues like
asthma nitrites are added to processed
Meats as preservatives to preserve their
pink so they don't turn gray keeping
them less rancid tasting and to present
the growth of diseases like botulism but
put that same sodium nitrate in the
drinking water of lab animals and they
develop empyema they nearly all
developed empa but that's all the
scientific knowledge we had on the
subject coming into 2007 until this
study which found that frequent cured
meat consumption is associated with
increased risk for developing diseases
like empyema in people too chronic
obstructive pulmonary disease eating it
like you know every other other day
appeared to Triple the odds of severe
COPD but it was just a snapshot in Time
study so we don't know which came first
the sausage or the COPD for that we need
prospective studies to follow people
over time and the big twin Harvard
studies and both women and men both
found that the risk of newly diagnosed
COPD increased with a greater
consumption of cured meats currently we
now have studies involving hundred
hundreds of thousands of people showing
that higher intakes of process meat were
associated with a 40% increased risk of
COPD it comes out to like an 8% high
risk of COPD for each hot dog you eat a
week or each weekly breakfast link
sausage what's going on yes there are
you know Advanced glycation M products
so called glycotoxins that may be
pro-inflammatory there's the saturated
fat that can also trigger inflammation
in the Airways the high salt content can
present a potential risk for lung
inflammation or the increase in systemic
inflammation in general but the reason
attention is focused on the nitrites is
because nitrites may actually be one of
the mechanisms by which tobacco smoke
causes diseases like empyema yes cured
meats are the principal source of
dietary nitrites but nitrites are also
byproducts of tobacco smoke one of the
main constituents besides the carbon
monoxide and nicotine are nitrogen
oxides that are converted in the lung to
nitrites the way nitrites appear to
cause lung damage is by affecting
connective tissue proteins like collagen
and elastin that's what helps keep the
air spaces in your lungs open but
nitride can modify these proteins in a
way that mimic age related damage
including the fragmentation of a
lasting with that much lung injury it's
logical to assume processed meat
consumption could also exacerbate the
disease of those who already have it and
indeed cured meat consumption increases
risk of COPD patients ending up back in
the hospital about twice the risk for
those eating more than average and
appears the more you eat the worse it
is regarding lung Health process meat
intake has been associated with a likely
increased risk of lung cancer a decline
in lung function and chronic obstructive
pulmonary diseases but what about asthma
High process meat consumption has been
associated with higher asthma symptoms
as well we knew about the higher
maternal intake of meat before pregnancy
potentially increasing the risk of
wheezing in her children later on based
on a study of more than a thousand
mother child Pairs and we're not talking
about aspirating meat into your lungs
and being misdiagnosed with asthma those
who eat the most cured meats were 76%
more likely to experience worsening
asthma than those who ate the least
since obesity is a likely risk factor
for asthma though maybe the influence of
the meat is just indirect by
contributing to weight gain uh that
might be a small part of it but the main
effect appears to be direct suggesting a
Delta role of cured meat independent of
weight put all those studies together
and process meat int appears to be an
important Target for the prevention of
adult asthma in the first
place even if you don't have any long
issues processed meat consumption was
negatively associated with measures of
normal lung function while fruit and
vegetable consumption in dietary total
antioxidant capacity was associated with
better lung
function but wait you say I just just
eat all natural uncured hot dogs with no
nitrates or nitrites added in all caps
but if you magnifying glass the small
print it says except those naturally
occurring in cultured celery juice see
to avoid saying they added nitrites what
they do is add something that has lots
of nitrates like celery and a bacteria
that converts the nitrates to nitrites
so they are adding nitrites they're just
just straight up duping
consumers we didn't add any nitrites
except of course for all the nitrites we
added we care about your health so no
nitrites added and who wants pepperoni
with nitrites so we just added lots of
nitrites we would never add any nitrites
now just let the piggy picture distract
you from the fact that we just lied to
your face
horel was my favorite except for those
naturally occurring in seasoning pretty
slick Europe doesn't allow this kind of
Consumer Fraud demanding manufacturers
explicitly label it as containing
nitrites I mean you can't even call it
natural when Consumer Reports put it to
the test they found the nitrite levels
in all the products was essentially the
same so no nitrites doesn't mean no
nitrites
consumer reports and the Center for
Science and the public interest have
petitioned to stop this misleading
practice nitrites are nitrites their
chemical composition is absolutely the
same and so are the health
[Music]
effects for